<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<items><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=45072&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Solar Storm on August 1, 2010</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/flare_stereoa_20102132126_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45072/flare_stereoa_20102132126_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/video/flare_stereoa_2010213-214_sm.mov">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45072/flare_stereoa_2010213-214_sm.mov</url><url localpath="media/video/flare_stereoa_2010213-214_lrg.mov">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45072/flare_stereoa_2010213-214_lrg.mov</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/flare_stereoa_20102132126.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45072/flare_stereoa_20102132126.jpg</url></media><shorttext>A flare bursts from the Sun in this detailed image taken on August 1, 2010, by the STEREO Ahead telescope. 
</shorttext><fulltext>Spectacular &lt;a href="http://sdoisgo.blogspot.com/2010/08/cme-hits-earth-and-causes-moderate.html"&gt;aurora&lt;/a&gt; lit the night sky from Europe to North America on August 3, 2010, thanks to a 12-hour long geomagnetic storm. The storm occurred as large clouds of charged particles from the Sun interacted with the magnetic field around Earth. As the particles zoomed along the magnetic field, they collided with and energized oxygen and nitrogen in the atmosphere. When the energized atoms relaxed, they emitted light, providing a brilliant show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The light display on August 3 started with a solar storm on August 1. This image, from NASA&amp;rsquo;s Solar Terrestrial Relations Observatory &lt;a href="http://stereo.gsfc.nasa.gov/"&gt;(STEREO)&lt;/a&gt; Ahead telescope, shows a small flare leaving the Sun in the upper left side of the image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun also sent a coronal mass ejection, a stream of charged particles, towards Earth about the same time as the flare occurred. The coronal mass ejection starts at 2:36 UTC and ends at 3:56 UTC on August 1 in this &lt;a href="/images/imagerecords/45000/45072/flare_stereoa_2010213-214_lrg.mov"&gt;animation&lt;/a&gt; on STEREO Ahead images. The coronal mass ejection happens quickly. It is the eruption of particles bursting from the left side of the Sun, just below the center. The animation shows the cloud of particles moving away toward Earth at more than 1,000 kilometers per second (3.6 million kilometers per hour or 2 million miles per hour), moving more quickly than any other coronal mass ejection in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flare and the coronal mass ejection were just two symptoms of solar activity on August 1. An &lt;a href="http://sdowww.lmsal.com/sdomedia/ssw/ssw_client/data/ssw_service_100801_043733_25581681/www/"&gt;animation,&lt;/a&gt; made from data from NASA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://sdo.gsfc.nasa.gov/"&gt;Solar Dynamics Observatory&lt;/a&gt; shows filaments of magnetism looping off the surface and a wave moving across the face of the Sun. Other activity on August 1 included large-scale shaking of the solar corona, radio bursts, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun goes through a regular activity cycle that lasts about 11 years, cycling between activity (solar maximum) and quiet (solar minimum). The last solar maximum was in 2001 followed by a long period of very little activity. The eruptions are among the first signs that the Sun is waking up and beginning to move towards another solar maximum, expected to occur in about 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="references"&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Reference&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;NASA. (2010, August 4). &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/topics/solarsystem/sunearthsystem/main/News080210-cme.html"&gt;Spacecraft observes coronal mass ejection.&lt;/a&gt; Accessed August 6, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;NASA images courtesy &lt;a href="http://stereo.gsfc.nasa.gov/"&gt;STEREO.&lt;/a&gt; Caption by Holli Riebeek.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;STEREO&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=45059&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Rabaul Caldera</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/rabaul_ali_2010165_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45059/rabaul_ali_2010165_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/rabaul_ali_2010165.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45059/rabaul_ali_2010165.jpg</url></media><shorttext>Acquired June 14, 2010, this natural-color image shows Rabaul Caldera on the northeastern tip of Papua New Guinea’s New Britain.</shorttext><fulltext>Volcanic cones and settlements mingle along the margins of the Rabaul Caldera on the northeastern tip of Papua New Guinea&amp;rsquo;s New Britain Island. Shaped like a giant cauldron, the caldera is the remaining rim of an ancient volcano. Small volcanic cones, some of which are still active, sit on the rim. Spanning roughly 8 by 14 kilometers (5 by 9 miles), the caldera is flooded by Blanche Bay. The largely submerged caldera long formed a natural harbor for what had been New Britain&amp;rsquo;s largest city, but a major eruption forced the evacuation of Rabaul City in 1994. Although the city ceased to bustle with activity, at least one volcanic cone remained active for years afterward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sparse cloud cover allowed the Advanced Land Imager &lt;a href="http://eo1.gsfc.nasa.gov/technology/alihome1.htm"&gt;(ALI)&lt;/a&gt; on NASA&amp;rsquo;s Earth Observing-1 &lt;a href="http://eo1.gsfc.nasa.gov/"&gt;(EO-1)&lt;/a&gt; this view of Rabaul Caldera on June 14, 2010. The landscape appears as a mixture of vegetated and bare ground. Vegetation almost completely coats the western side of Rabaul Caldera. Volcanic cones line the northeastern margin of the caldera, and around these cones, the land is mostly rocky and barren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tavurvur, near the southern end of the exposed caldera rim, was one of the volcanoes to erupt explosively in 1994. The other was Vulcan, on the western side of the caldera. While vegetation has revived on the slopes of Vulcan, rocks predominate at Tavurvur, evidence of more recent eruptive activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remnants of settlements linger along the caldera&amp;rsquo;s northwestern margin and on a promontory near the caldera&amp;rsquo;s center. Prior to the explosive eruption in 1994, the city of Rabaul and been the provincial capital of East New Britain. After the eruption, the capital was moved to the coastal city of Kokopo, some 20 kilometers (12 miles) to the southeast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="references"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Global Volcanism Program. &lt;a href="http://www.volcano.si.edu/world/volcano.cfm?vnum=0502-14="&gt;Rabaul Volcano.&lt;/a&gt; Smithsonian  Institution. Accessed August 5, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seach, J. &lt;a href="http://www.volcanolive.com/rabaul.html"&gt;Rabaul Volcano.&lt;/a&gt; Accessed August 5, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volcano World. &lt;a href="http://volcano.oregonstate.edu/vwdocs/volc_images/img_rabaul.html"&gt;Tavurvur, Rabaul Caldera, New Britain Island, Papua New Guinea.&lt;/a&gt; Oregon State University. Accessed August 5, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wikipedia. (2010, July 21). &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rabaul"&gt;Rabaul.&lt;/a&gt; Accessed August 5, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;NASA Earth Observatory image created by Jesse Allen, using EO-1 ALI data provided courtesy of &lt;a href="http://eo1.gsfc.nasa.gov/"&gt;the NASA EO-1 team.&lt;/a&gt; Caption by Michon Scott.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;EO-1 - ALI&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=45046&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Fires and Smoke in Russia</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/Russia_TMO_2010216_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45046/Russia_TMO_2010216_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/Moscow_TMO_2010216.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45046/Moscow_TMO_2010216.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/Russia_TMO_2010216.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45046/Russia_TMO_2010216.jpg</url></media><shorttext>This photo-like image from August 4, 2010, shows intense fires burning across central Russia and a thick plume of smoke stretching about 3,000 kilometers (1,860 miles).</shorttext><fulltext>Intense fires continued to rage in western Russia on August 4, 2010. Burning in dry peat bogs and forests, the fires produced a dense plume of smoke that reached across hundreds of kilometers. The Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer &lt;a href="http://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;(MODIS)&lt;/a&gt; captured this view of the fires and smoke in three consecutive overpasses on NASA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://terra.nasa.gov/"&gt;Terra&lt;/a&gt;  satellite. The smooth gray-brown smoke hangs over the Russian landscape, completely obscuring the ground in places. The top image provides a close view of the fires immediately southeast of Moscow, while the lower image shows the full extent of the smoke plume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fires along the southern edge of the smoke plume near the city of Razan, top image, are among the most intense. Outlined in red, a line of intense fires is generating a wall of smoke. The easternmost fire in the image is extreme enough that it produced a &lt;a href="http://amsglossary.allenpress.com/glossary/search?p=1&amp;query=pyrocumulus&amp;submit=Search"&gt;pyrocumulus cloud,&lt;/a&gt; a dense towering cloud formed when intense heat from a fire pushes air high into the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The lower image shows the full extent of the smoke plume, spanning about 3,000 kilometers (1,860 miles) from east to west. If the smoke were in the United States, it would extend approximately from San Francisco to Chicago. The MODIS sensor acquired the right section of the image starting at 5:55 UTC (10:55 a.m. local time, 8:55 a.m. in Moscow). The center section is from the overpass starting at 7:35 UTC (11:35 local time, 10:35 in Moscow), and the westernmost section was taken at 9:10 UTC (12:10 p.m. local time in Moscow).&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Early analyses of data from the Multi-angle Imaging Spectroradiometer (MISR), another instrument on the Terra satellite, indicates that smoke from previous days has at times reached 12 kilometers (six miles) above Earth&amp;rsquo;s surface into the stratosphere. At such heights, smoke is able to travel long distances to affect air quality far away. This may be one reason that the smoke covers such a large area. The pyrocumulus cloud and the detection of smoke in the stratosphere are good indicators that the fires are large and extremely intense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to news reports, 520 fires were burning in western Russia on August 4. MODIS detected far fewer. It is likely that the remaining fires were hidden from the satellite&amp;rsquo;s view by the thick smoke and scattered clouds. &lt;a href="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=44664"&gt;High temperatures&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/NaturalHazards/view.php?id=44743"&gt;severe drought&lt;/a&gt; dried vegetation throughout central Russia, creating hazardous fire conditions in July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of August 4, 48 people had died in the fires and more than 2,000 had lost their homes throughout central Russia, said news reports. The dense smoke also created hazardous air quality over a broad region. Visibility in Moscow dropped to 20 meters (0.01 miles) on August 4, and health officials warned that everyone, including healthy people, needed to take preventative measures such as staying indoors or wearing a mask outdoors, reported the Wall Street Journal. In the image, Moscow is hidden under a pall of smoke. Close to the fires, smoke poses a health risk because it contains small particles (soot) and hazardous gases that can irritate the eyes and respiratory system. Smoke also contains chemicals that lead to ozone production farther away from the fires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The large image provides the full scene shown in the lower image at the sensor&amp;rsquo;s highest resolution (as shown in the top image). The MODIS Rapid Response Team provides the scene in &lt;a href="http://rapidfire.sci.gsfc.nasa.gov/gallery/?2010216-0804/Russia.A2010216.0915.2km.jpg"&gt;additional resolutions.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="references"&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BBC News. (2010, August 4). &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-10865316"&gt;Medvedev cuts holiday as Russian wildfires kill 48.&lt;/a&gt; Accessed August 4, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iosebashvili, I. (2010, August 4). &lt;a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704017904575408833952872038.html"&gt;Death toll rises as Russian fires rage.&lt;/a&gt; Wall Street Journal. Accessed August 4, 2010.&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ol&gt;

		&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href="/NaturalHazards/event.php?id=44953"&gt;More images of this event in Natural Hazards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
		
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;NASA image courtesy Jeff Schmaltz, &lt;a href="http://rapidfire.sci.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;MODIS Rapid Response Team&lt;/a&gt; at NASA GSFC. Caption by Holli Riebeek with information courtesy Mike Fromm, Naval Research Laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;Terra - MODIS&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=45041&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Oil Slick, Mississippi River Delta, Gulf of Mexico</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/ISS024-E-009404_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45041/ISS024-E-009404_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/ISS024-E-009404.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/45000/45041/ISS024-E-009404.jpg</url></media><shorttext>Photograph of a portion the oil slick in the Gulf of Mexico taken by an astronaut aboard the International Space Station on July 23, 2010.
</shorttext><fulltext>The International Space Station (ISS) observed the Gulf of Mexico oil spill in late July 2010, as part of ongoing observations of the region. When this image was taken, three months after the explosion on the Deepwater Horizon oil rig, the leak had been plugged for eight days. Water surfaces appear bright and land surfaces appear dark in the image. The stark contrast is due to &lt;a href="/Glossary/?xref=sunglint"&gt;sunglint,&lt;/a&gt; in which the Sun is reflected off water surfaces back towards the astronaut observer on board the ISS. The sunglint reveals various features in the Gulf of Mexico, especially sheens of oil that appear as packets of long bright streaks (image right). Sediments carried by the Mississippi River have a pale beige coloration in this image, with distinct margins between plumes that likely mark tidal pulses of river water into the Gulf of Mexico. A boat wake cuts across one of the oil packets at image top right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bright waterways known as the South and Southwest Passes of the tip of the Mississippi River Delta (image center left and lower left) provide passage for ships into the Gulf of Mexico. The section of South Pass shown in the image is 8 miles (13 km) long. This gives a sense of the proximity of the ruined Deepwater Horizon oil rig, which is located only 50 miles (80 km) to the southeast of the imaged area (not shown.) Daily maps of oil distribution produced by NOAA show predicted heavier and lighter oil movement near the Gulf coastline. The map from &lt;a href="http://response.restoration.noaa.gov/book_shelf/2339_TMF24-2010-07-22-2100.pdf"&gt;July 22, 2010,&lt;/a&gt; (PDF file) shows that on the day this image was taken from the ISS (July 23, 2010), the north edge of the &amp;ldquo;oiled&amp;rdquo; zone was expected to bank up against the Delta. The observed spread of the surface oil in the approximately 100 days since the explosion highlights the connectivity between the deep-water areas and coastlines of the Gulf of Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about oil slick images shown on the Earth Observatory, including why the oil isn&amp;rsquo;s visible every day, please visit &lt;a href="/Features/OilSlick/"&gt;Gulf of Mexico Oil Slick Images: Frequently Asked Questions.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href="/NaturalHazards/event.php?id=43733"&gt;More images of this event in Natural Hazards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
		
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;Astronaut photograph &lt;a href="http://eol.jsc.nasa.gov/scripts/sseop/photo.pl?mission=ISS024&amp;roll=E&amp;frame=9404"&gt;ISS024-E-9404&lt;/a&gt; July 23, 2010, with a Nikon D2Xs digital camera using a 400 mm lens, and is provided by the ISS Crew Earth Observations experiment and Image Science &amp; Analysis Laboratory, Johnson Space Center. The image was taken by the &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/expeditions/expedition24/index.html"&gt;Expedition 24 crew.&lt;/a&gt; The image in this article has been cropped and enhanced to improve contrast. Lens artifacts have been removed. The &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/science/nlab/index.html"&gt;International Space Station Program&lt;/a&gt; supports the laboratory as part of the &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/science/nlab/index.html"&gt;ISS National Lab&lt;/a&gt; to help astronauts take pictures of Earth that will be of the greatest value to scientists and the public, and to make those images freely available on the Internet. Additional images taken by astronauts and cosmonauts can be viewed at the NASA/JSC &lt;a href="http://eol.jsc.nasa.gov"&gt;Gateway to Astronaut Photography of Earth.&lt;/a&gt; Caption by M. Justin Wilkinson, NASA-JSC.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;ISS - Digital Camera&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=44991&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Flooding in Pakistan</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/pakistan_tmo_2010212_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44991/pakistan_tmo_2010212_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/large/pakistan_tmo_2009213_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44991/pakistan_tmo_2009213_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/pakistan_tmo_2010212.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44991/pakistan_tmo_2010212.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/pakistan_tmo_2009213.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44991/pakistan_tmo_2009213.jpg</url></media><shorttext>Acquired on July 31, 2010 (top), and August 2, 2009 (bottom), these false-color images show the dramatic difference caused by torrential monsoon rains in 2010. The area pictured is where the Indus River veers toward the west on its journey toward the coast.</shorttext><fulltext>Monsoon rains fall in Pakistan every summer, but the rains beginning in late July 2010 were unusually heavy. By August 1, 2010, entire villages had washed away, more than 1,100 people had died, and an estimated 2.5 million people were affected, according to news reports. A shortage of safe drinking water and a possible outbreak of cholera were among the most pressing dangers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer &lt;a href="http://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;(MODIS)&lt;/a&gt; on NASA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://terra.nasa.gov"&gt;Terra&lt;/a&gt; satellite captured these images on July 31, 2010 (top), and August 1, 2009 (bottom). These images show the Indus River in northwestern Pakistan. Both images use a combination of infrared and visible light to increase the contrast between water and land. Water varies in color from electric blue to navy. Vegetation is green and bare ground is pinkish brown. Clouds range in color from nearly white to pale blue-green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acquired at the same time of year, the images show the dramatic difference caused by torrential monsoon rains. Flowing roughly north-south the Indus River appears as a braided stream in 2009, with patches of dry or nearly dry ground in the river valley. In 2010, the water level is high enough to cover areas that were dry the previous year. West of the river, long tendrils of standing water extend toward the northwest. Water levels are also significantly higher in tributaries east of the Indus River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officials described the flooding in northwestern Pakistan as the worst since 1929. News reports documented some 30,000 residents stranded on rooftops, and some 65 bridges completely washed away. As governments and international aid organizations struggled to assist the flood victims, weather officials forecast more monsoon rains starting August 2, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MODIS provides daily images, where clouds permit, that enable responders to assess flood conditions over a wide area in a single satellite pass. The MODIS Rapid Response Team provides &lt;a href="http://rapidfire.sci.gsfc.nasa.gov/subsets/?subset=FAS_India1"&gt;daily images&lt;/a&gt; of this region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="references"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ACT Alliance. (2010, July 29). &lt;a href="http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/rwb.nsf/db900SID/ASHU-87TP7A?OpenDocument&amp;clickid=headlines"&gt;Thousands stranded by Pakistan floods.&lt;/a&gt; ReliefWeb. Accessed August 2, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BBC. (2010, August 2). &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-10834414"&gt;&amp;ldquo;2.5m people affected&amp;rdquo; by Pakistan floods officials say.&lt;/a&gt; Accessed August 2, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CNN. (2010, August 1). &lt;a href="http://www.cnn.com/2010/WORLD/asiapcf/08/01/pakistan.flooding.deaths/?hpt=T1"&gt;Officials: Pakistan flood deaths top 1,100.&lt;/a&gt; Accessed August 2, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Masood, S. (2010, July 31). &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/01/world/asia/01pstan.html"&gt;Floods in Pakistan kill at least 800.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;cite&gt;The New York Times.&lt;/cite&gt; Accessed August 2, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

		&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href="/NaturalHazards/event.php?id=44986"&gt;More images of this event in Natural Hazards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
		
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;NASA images courtesy the &lt;a href="http://rapidfire.sci.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;MODIS Rapid Response Team&lt;/a&gt; at NASA GSFC. Caption by Michon Scott.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;Terra - MODIS&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=44982&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Kaziranga National Park, India</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/kaziranga_etm_2000036_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44982/kaziranga_etm_2000036_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/kaziranga_etm_2000036.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44982/kaziranga_etm_2000036.jpg</url></media><shorttext>In the Indian state of Assam, Kaziranga National Park protects a few hundred square miles of the Brahmaputra River's floodplain.</shorttext><fulltext>In the state of Assam, in the northeastern corner of India, Kaziranga National Park protects a few hundred square miles of the Brahmaputra River&amp;rsquo;s natural floodplain.  In the fertile soil washed down from the Himalaya Mountains during the &lt;a href="/IOTD/view.php?id=8042 "&gt;yearly floods,&lt;/a&gt; lush grasses grow up to 20 feet high, making the park a paradise for grazing animals and their predators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This natural-color image from the Landsat satellite shows Kaziranga National Park on February 5, 2000. The river flows west through braided channels interspersed with sandy islands. The grassy expanse of the park to the south is dotted with pools of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hilly terrain on both sides of the river plays an important role in making the park a wildlife haven.  When snowmelt and summer monsoon rains flood the lowlands, the residents—which include endangered rhinos, elephants, wild water buffalos, and tigers—migrate from the river corridor to higher ground. Small reserves and sanctuaries protect some of the forested hills south of Kaziranga, but villages and fields are mixed among them, which means that human-wildlife conflicts are inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="references"&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Chadwick, D. (2010, August). India&amp;rsquo;s Grassland Kingdom. &lt;cite&gt;National Geographic,&lt;/cite&gt; 218(2), 98-117.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;NASA image by Robert Simmon, based on &lt;a href="http://landsat.gsfc.nasa.gov/"&gt;Landsat-7&lt;/a&gt; data from the USGS &lt;a href="http://glovis.usgs.gov/"&gt;Global Visualization Viewer,&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://www.wdpa.org/Default.aspx"&gt;World Database on Protected Areas.&lt;/a&gt; Caption by Rebecca Lindsey.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;Landsat 7 - ETM+&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=44972&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Neumayer Glacier, South Georgia Island</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/sgeorgiais_ali_2005011_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44972/sgeorgiais_ali_2005011_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/large/sgeorgiais_ali_2009004_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44972/sgeorgiais_ali_2009004_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/sgeorgiais_ali_2005011.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44972/sgeorgiais_ali_2005011.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/sgeorgiais_ali_2009004.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44972/sgeorgiais_ali_2009004.jpg</url></media><shorttext>Acquired January 11, 2005 and January 4, 2009, these images show retreat in the Neumayer Glacier on South Georgia Island.</shorttext><fulltext>South Georgia is an arc-shaped island that lies some 2,000 kilometers (1,200 miles) east of the southern tip of South America. Along South Georgia&amp;rsquo;s east coast, Neumayer Glacier has long snaked toward the ocean, occasionally calving icebergs. Prior to 1970, observations of the ice front&amp;rsquo;s position showed changes in just tens of meters, but the glacier subsequently began losing significant mass, according to a study published in 2008. From roughly 1970 to 2002, Neumayer retreated by roughly 2 kilometers (1.2 miles). As the first decade of the twenty-first century wore on, Neumayer continued losing ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Advanced Land Imager &lt;a href="http://eo1.gsfc.nasa.gov/technology/alihome1.htm"&gt;(ALI)&lt;/a&gt; on NASA&amp;rsquo;s Earth Observing-1 &lt;a href="http://eo1.gsfc.nasa.gov/"&gt;(EO-1)&lt;/a&gt; satellite captured these natural-color images of the glacier on South Georgia on January 11, 2005 (top), and January 4, 2009 (bottom). In the four years that elapsed between ALI&amp;rsquo;s observations, the glacier retreated approximately 1 kilometer (0.6 miles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides reducing the glacier&amp;rsquo;s length, the retreat apparently affected the crevasses (cracks in the ice) upstream on the glacier. The 2009 image shows wider crevasses that extend more toward the east, especially along the glacier&amp;rsquo;s southern margin. The shifted crevasse pattern suggests possible glacier acceleration in the wake of the breakup of the ice front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A glacier that extends all the way to the sea while remaining grounded is a tidewater glacier, and the largest glaciers on South Georgia Island, including Neumayer, are tidewater glaciers. Even a tiny change in ocean temperature, whether daily, seasonal, or interannual, translates into a substantial change in the amount of heat available to melt tidewater glaciers. An increase in temperature can cause a cascading effect of changes in calving rate, ice front position, and glacier flow. Changes in glacier flow can manifest as visible changes to the crevasses on the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides changes in the glacier, other variations appear between 2005 and 2009. Although acquired at the same time of year, the image from 2009 shows more snow cover around the stream of ice, which could simply be from a snowstorm immediately before that ALI observation. A thin veil of clouds hangs over the region in 2005, whereas skies are clear in 2009, except for some isolated clouds in the northeast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="references"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gordon, J.E., Haynes, V.M., Hubbard, A. (2008). &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gloplacha.2006.07.037"&gt; Recent glacier changes and climate trends on South Georgia.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;cite&gt;Global and Planetary Change,&lt;/cite&gt; 60, 72&amp;ndash;84.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;NASA Earth Observatory image created by Jesse Allen, using EO-1 ALI data provided courtesy of &lt;a href="http://eo1.gsfc.nasa.gov/"&gt;the NASA EO-1 team.&lt;/a&gt; Caption by Michon Scott, based on image interpretation by Ted Scambos, National Snow and Ice Data Center.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;EO-1 - ALI&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=44978&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Earth from the Moon</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/earth_lro_2010163_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44978/earth_lro_2010163_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/large/earth_lro_2010163_bluemarble_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44978/earth_lro_2010163_bluemarble_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/earth_lro_2010163.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44978/earth_lro_2010163.jpg</url></media><shorttext>Orbiting the Moon 372,335 kilometers away from Earth, the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter captured this image of Earth on June 12, 2010.</shorttext><fulltext>Summer was approaching in the Northern Hemisphere on June 12, 2010, when the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter looked home to acquire this image. In orbit around the Moon, the orbiter was about 372,335 kilometers from Earth. Skies over the Middle East were clear, providing a cloud-free view of Arabian Peninsula and the mountains of Iran and Pakistan. Bright clouds stretch in a line from India northeast over the North Pacific Ocean. The other bright region in the image is the polar ice cap over the Arctic Ocean. The reference map provides a cloud-free view to illustrate Earth&amp;rsquo;s orientation in the image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter Camera captured this image as part of a calibration exercise. Like the human eye, the camera records reflected light. The cameras are among seven instruments that are mapping the surface of the Moon from the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter, which orbits 50 kilometers above the Moon. Mapping the Moon is a challenge because its color does not change greatly. Changes in rock types provide only small shifts in color. To make sure that the cameras are accurately recording small changes in reflected light, engineers look for a bright light against a dark background to provide a reference point. From the Moon, Earth is an ideal reference point to calibrate the cameras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Narrow Angle Cameras&amp;mdash;the cameras designed to capture the most detailed images of the Moon&amp;mdash;took this image during calibration. The image is a mosaic of the views recorded by the Narrow Angle Camera Left and Narrow Angle Camera Right. The bottom of the Earth is clipped because the prediction of the exact time when the cameras&amp;rsquo; fields of view would cross the Earth was off by a few seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="references"&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Reference&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robinson, M. (2010, June 24). &lt;a href="http://lroc.sese.asu.edu/news/index.php?/archives/249-The-Earth-from-the-Moon.html#extended"&gt;The Earth from the Moon.&lt;/a&gt; Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter Camera, NASA. Accessed July 30, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;Image courtesy NASA/Goddard/Arizona State University. Map by Robert Simmon. Caption by Holli Riebeek.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;LRO - NAC&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=44969&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Oil Slick in the Gulf of Mexico</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/gulf_amo_2010209_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44969/gulf_amo_2010209_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/gulf_amo_2010209.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44969/gulf_amo_2010209.jpg</url></media><shorttext>Acquired July 28, 2010, this natural-color image shows possible oil patches near the Mississippi Delta.</shorttext><fulltext>On July 24, 2010, the administrator of the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), Jane Lubchenco, provided a &lt;a href="http://app.restorethegulf.gov/go/doc/2931/821855/"&gt;briefing&lt;/a&gt; about the anticipated impact of &lt;a href="/NaturalHazards/view.php?id=44753"&gt;Tropical Storm Bonnie&lt;/a&gt; on the Deepwater Horizon oil slick in the Gulf of Mexico. Bonnie was expected to help dissipate and weather the oil on the sea surface, spreading out the slick, lowering surface concentrations, and making the oil more amenable to biodegradation. On July 28, 2010, after Bonnie had passed through the region, NOAA reported less oil observed on Gulf of Mexico overflights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer &lt;a href="http://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;(MODIS)&lt;/a&gt; on NASA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://aqua.nasa.gov"&gt;Aqua&lt;/a&gt; satellite captured this natural-color image on July 28, 2010. Around the location of the oil leak, and around the Mississippi Delta, relatively light swirls and patches appear on the ocean surface. These areas might be oil slicks, although other factors could affect the water&amp;rsquo;s ability to reflect sunlight, especially near the shore. If these pale-hued sheens are oil-slicked areas, they contain very little recoverable oil, according to NOAA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months since the Deepwater Horizon accident, the Earth Observatory has been able to show oil slicks in the Gulf of Mexico only under certain conditions, namely clear skies and sunlight hitting the water at an appropriate angle. To learn more about our oil slick images, including why the oil isn&amp;rsquo;s visible every day, please visit &lt;a href="/Features/OilSlick/"&gt;Gulf of Mexico Oil Slick Images: Frequently Asked Questions.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="references"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Related Resources&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.restorethegulf.gov/"&gt;RestoreTheGulf.gov&lt;/a&gt; is the official federal portal for the Deepwater BP oil spill response and recovery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://response.restoration.noaa.gov/topic_subtopic_entry.php?RECORD_KEY%28entry_subtopic_topic%29=entry_id,subtopic_id,topic_id&amp;entry_id%28entry_subtopic_topic%29=809&amp;subtopic_id%28entry_subtopic_topic%29=2&amp;topic_id%28entry_subtopic_topic%29=1"&gt;Current information about the extent of the oil slick&lt;/a&gt; is available from the Office of Response and Restoration at the National Oceanic and Atmosphere Administration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.fws.gov/home/dhoilspill/index.html"&gt;Information about the impact of the oil slick on wildlife&lt;/a&gt; is provided by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

		&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href="/NaturalHazards/event.php?id=43733"&gt;More images of this event in Natural Hazards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
		
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;NASA image by Jeff Schmaltz, &lt;a href="http://rapidfire.sci.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;MODIS Rapid Response Team.&lt;/a&gt; Caption by Michon Scott.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;Aqua - MODIS&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item><item link="http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=44958&amp;src=iotdrss"><title>Bull Fire in California’s Sequoia National Forest</title><media><url localpath="media/img/large/California_AMO_2010208_lrg.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44958/California_AMO_2010208_lrg.jpg</url><url localpath="media/img/reg/California_AMO_2010208.jpg">http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/44000/44958/California_AMO_2010208.jpg</url></media><shorttext>Outlined in red in this true-color image from July 27, 2010, the Bull Fire produced thick plumes of smoke as it burned near the southern edge of the Sequoia National Forest in southern California.</shorttext><fulltext>The fast-growing Bull Fire burned on the southern edge of California&amp;rsquo;s Sequoia National Forest on July 27, 2010. Outlined in red, the fire was producing thick plumes of smoke when the Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer &lt;a href="http://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;(MODIS)&lt;/a&gt; on NASA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://aqua.nasa.gov/"&gt;Aqua&lt;/a&gt; satellite captured this image at 2:40 p.m. U.S. Pacific Time. The smoke was blowing north over the forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bull Fire started on Monday, July 26 at about 1:46 a.m., according to the multi-agency incident report for the fire. Burning through grass, brush, oak, and scattered pine and aided by high temperatures, the fire grew quickly on steep, hard-to-access ground. As of about 10 p.m. on July 27, the fire had burned 11,000 acres, said the incident report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fire forced evacuations in the community of Riverkern, where six homes were destroyed, reported CNN. The Bull Fire was one of two large fires burning in Kern County on July 27. Though the cause is still under investigation, the fire may have been started by people, said the incident report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sequoia National Forest is at the southern end of the Sierra Nevada range. In this image, the mountains are covered in deep green forest. The snow-capped peaks north of the fire are dingy brown and partially obscured by smoke. To the west of the mountains is San Joaquin Valley, the southern half of the Central Valley. The valley is checkered with green farm fields and dotted with gray cities and towns. In the rain shadow of the Sierra Nevada, the land to the east is mostly desert brown and tan. This area is Death Valley National Park, which is part of the Mojave Desert. The Nevada state line cuts across the upper right corner of the image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MODIS Rapid Response Team provides &lt;a href="http://rapidfire.sci.gsfc.nasa.gov/subsets/?subset=AERONET_Fresno.2010208"&gt;twice-daily images&lt;/a&gt; of southern California. The large image is the highest-resolution version of the image, but the image is available in additional resolutions from the MODIS Rapid Response Team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="references"&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CNN. (2010, July 28). &lt;a href="http://www.cnn.com/2010/US/07/28/california.wildfires.spread/index.html?hpt=Sbin"&gt;Wildfires spark state of emergency in California county. &lt;/a&gt; Accessed July 28, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dillon, R.M. (2010, July 28). &lt;a href="http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20100728/ap_on_re_us/us_california_wildfires"&gt;California wildfires burn about 40 homes, threaten 150.&lt;/a&gt; Associated Press. Accessed July 28, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;InciWeb. (2010, July 27). &lt;a href="http://inciweb.org/incident/2043/"&gt;Bull Fire.&lt;/a&gt; Accessed July 28, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;U.S. Forest Service. (2010, July 27). &lt;a href="http://www.fs.fed.us/r5/sequoia/"&gt;Sequoia National Forest.&lt;/a&gt; Accessed July 28, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

		&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href="/NaturalHazards/event.php?id=44959"&gt;More images of this event in Natural Hazards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
		
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class="credit"&gt;NASA image courtesy the &lt;a href="http://rapidfire.sci.gsfc.nasa.gov"&gt;MODIS Rapid Response Team&lt;/a&gt; at NASA GSFC. Caption by Holli Riebeek.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;dl class="details"&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;Instrument:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;Aqua - MODIS&lt;/dd&gt;

	&lt;/dl&gt;
	
</fulltext></item></items>